<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <description>Writing in Public</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 15:09:59 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 15:09:59 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.0.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>How to Become Healthier and More Productive Through Self Tracking Without Spending Hundreds of Dollars</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2476/1*LlFLOHQR0vg6cVOgZn5XFg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From steps, to sleep, to time spent online. Every day you’re generating data which has the power to inform and shape the way you live your life. For those willing to seek, lies a treasure trove of personal insights waiting to be discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article we’ll cover:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Why you should start tracking your data &lt;em&gt;today,&lt;/em&gt; in order to take advantage of compounding effects&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What to track, and how to use this data to make better data-informed decisions&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How to build robust tracking systems that will stand the test of time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll also talk about my journey and key learnings from quantified self over the last 6 years, along with the tools I’ve built and open-sourced, such as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/andreilys/personal_dashboard&quot;&gt;real-time personal dashboard&lt;/a&gt;, weekly check-in bot and a daily journal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-you-should-start-tracking-today&quot;&gt;Why you should start tracking today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite our best intentions, human memory is fallible. Countless studies have proven that we simply cannot rely on our memories for an accurate picture of the past. You might look back on your week and feel accomplished, but if you dug into the data the story might be quite different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantified self helps remedy this problem by identifying metrics which are trackable and can act as signals that we’re on the right track. With data, you can hold yourself accountable. If you commit to three workouts a week, you can catalog your progress rather than rely on memory alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another benefit of tracking data, is that it gets more valuable as it grows in volume. It can help you identify patterns that would otherwise go undetected. For example, you may notice that while traveling your meditation time drops. This may lead you to implement a new meditation travel protocol to ensure you hit your goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also act as a historical capsule to get a sense of who your past self was, and how you’ve changed over the years. Whether it’s the websites you’ve visited, or the locations you’ve frequented, all this can act as a way to get a sense of where you’ve been, and where you’re going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-to-track&quot;&gt;What to Track&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you choose to track is a byproduct of how much time and money you’d like to commit to self-tracking. The great thing with quantified self is that you can start with a paper and pen, tracking something as simple as your workouts. For those who are lazy, we have technology which can help automate the tracking process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases, it’s recommended that people start with apps like &lt;a href=&quot;https://gyrosco.pe/&quot;&gt;Gyroscope&lt;/a&gt; which has both a free and paid tier. Apps like Gyroscope serve as general-purpose data aggregators, providing slick visualizations of your data, which make the process of collecting, and understanding your data a lot easier. They have a variety of integrations with third party data providers, and have an intuitive user interface that makes it easy to identify trends to take action on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*yqtk5iRX4gH1_bySt2XVZQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;[Gyroscope](https://gyrosco.pe/)&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gyrosco.pe/&quot;&gt;Gyroscope&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those with technical skills, you can access your data through API’s from services and websites that you use. Below are some examples of things I track:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Time spent online — &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rescuetime.com/&quot;&gt;Rescuetime&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Focus time — &lt;a href=&quot;https://toggl.com/&quot;&gt;Toggl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Workouts, weight, steps — &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.withings.com/&quot;&gt;Withings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Meditation — &lt;a href=&quot;https://insighttimer.com/&quot;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Workouts, weight, steps — &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.withings.com/&quot;&gt;Withings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Finances — &lt;a href=&quot;https://statusmoney.com/&quot;&gt;Status Money&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Books — &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/&quot;&gt;Goodreads&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Writing — &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/&quot;&gt;Medium&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Programming — &lt;a href=&quot;https://wakatime.com/&quot;&gt;Wakatime&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This data is then aggregated and summarized in three different ways. One is through a dashboard that I have in the corner of my room. This gives me context on how my day is going and whether I’m on track to hit my daily goals. The other is my daily evening journal which uses a &lt;a href=&quot;https://vimwiki.github.io&quot;&gt;vimwiki&lt;/a&gt; template to grab all my data for the day, giving me another opportunity to reflect on my day. Finally we have a Facebook Messenger bot that pings me on Sundays with the results of the week. Responding to this bot via Messenger with my reflections is then captured in a Google spreadsheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2624/1*I6PKAnzVrdFrPO3r5r7gJA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;making-better-decisions&quot;&gt;Making Better Decisions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quantified self can help with both micro day-to-day decision making, as well as macro life-altering decisions. In my case, the immediate impact of seeing how I’m spending my day based on the real-time dashboard I have helps me adjust accordingly. If I see that I’m approaching my daily limit for unproductive time on my computer, I can take evasive action to prevent a loss in my daily goals streak. Jerry Seinfeld used the same technique by marking a physical calendar every day that he wrote new comedic material. In this way, he would build momentum and avoid &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.writersstore.com/dont-break-the-chain-jerry-seinfeld/&quot;&gt;“breaking chain”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2208/1*Ang8HOeKHkNrTS9WzxNYKQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are three other data-driven decisions I’ve made with the help of quantified self:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Accomplishing Internal Goals&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading through my journals, I realized that the days where I felt most nourished were the days that I spent focusing, meditating and not having my attention get hijacked by time-wasting sites. To that end, I decided to setup some internal goals which consist of spending 2.5 hours focusing (&lt;a href=&quot;https://toggl.com/&quot;&gt;Toggl&lt;/a&gt;), 20mins meditating (&lt;a href=&quot;https://insighttimer.com/&quot;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt;), and less than 1 hour on unproductive websites (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rescuetime.com/&quot;&gt;RescueTime&lt;/a&gt;). After implementing these measures and building out a dashboard to track this, I was able to make better micro-decisions around how I spent my day, which significantly affected the macro-outlook of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scheduled Walks&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always viewed myself as a fairly active person and am well aware of the risks of a sedentary lifestyle. That’s why I was surprised when I learned I was walking less than 5000 steps a day. Noticing this pattern, I decided to take action and implement a solution. Each afternoon, when I would typically experience a drop in productivity, I blocked off 30 minutes to go for a walk. This served as a natural break in the day, which resulted in increased steps, and a much more productive afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Limiting Online Communications&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at the visualization of my Rescue Time data, I realized how frequently I checked email and social media throughout the day. To combat this, I purged my phone of apps that weren’t necessary and disabled notifications on everything that wasn’t essential. I also implemented content blocking through the&lt;a href=&quot;https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT201304&quot;&gt; iOS content restriction feature&lt;/a&gt;, and installed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/go-fucking-work/hibmkkpfegfiinilnlabbfnjcopdiiig?hl=en&quot;&gt;Chrome extension&lt;/a&gt; whose purpose was to block me from visiting unproductive sites during work hours. I also experimented with phone-free Sunday’s, with the help of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Kitchen-Safe-Locking-Container-Height/dp/B00JGFQTD2&quot;&gt;timed-lock box&lt;/a&gt;, which would prevent me from using my phone until the time I set expired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-three-rules-for-quantified-self&quot;&gt;My Three Rules for Quantified Self&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tracking-must-be-frictionless&quot;&gt;Tracking must be frictionless&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a firm proponent of lazy tracking, which requires little to no input from you. Having spent years trying out various quantified self apps, I’ve come to the conclusion that anything requiring manual input from me is going to fail long term. When I consider adding a new data source, I always ask myself “Will I still be doing this 5 years from now?”. In this way I’m able to build robust systems that I can commit to for the long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;theres-a-process-in-place-to-review-my-data-and-make-decisions&quot;&gt;There’s a process in place to review my data and make decisions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a dashboard in the corner of my room displaying my goals forces me to review and make adjustments during my day. Same thing with my daily journal and weekly check-in bot, I get messaged and can review the data without much hassle. Having a proper feedback loop will ensure that you get the most out of your personal data collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;embracing-open-data&quot;&gt;Embracing open data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my guiding principles for integrating a new data source is that the website or device must have an API or way of exporting the data. Too many quantified self devices and websites lock down your data behind proprietary systems. Typically the visualization tools are limited and there is a very real chance of the company shutting down or being acquired. Once that happens, all the data that you built up over the years is as good as gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adhering to these three rules is what has helped me stick with my current quantified self system for over 3 years now. Where before I had many false starts, now I’m much more consistent and systematic in the way I collect and review my data. This ensures that I will be much more likely to comply long-term, it also allows me to evaluate future extensions of the data this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you go about setting up your own tracking system, I encourage you to keep iterating and improving on your system.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/how-to-become-healthier-and-more-productive-through-self-tracking-without-spending-hundreds-of-dollars/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/how-to-become-healthier-and-more-productive-through-self-tracking-without-spending-hundreds-of-dollars/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Three Stages of a Data Scientist</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2312/0*ahgwx-_d2b5Rrq7M&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best and worst parts of being a data scientist is the ambiguity that the role can often entail. Since data science is a relatively new function, the mandate and objectives aren’t always clear. This often means that the destiny of data science at a company lies in the hands of the data scientists, who often find themselves straddling both technical and non-technical domains. As such, being able to shape and define the role is key if you want to have a fulfilling career as a data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we’ll explore the progression that a data scientist makes throughout their career, starting with Decision Support, Advisor and then Integrated Partner. We’ll go over their characteristics, some examples, and how you can progress through each stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;decision-support&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Decision Support&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dynamic that you have at the decision support stage is similar to a ticketing system, where you’re fulfilling requests with simple data extracts and leaving insights to the stakeholder. At this stage, the relationship you have with your stakeholders is subservient. You’re unlikely to push back or provide input on what you should be working on or what the company as a whole should focus on. The work is reactive, and your roadmap consists of whatever your stakeholders are asking for that week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;advisor&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advisor&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advisor, on the other hand, acts as a thought partner. Instead of receiving and fulfilling requests, advisors take the time to understand the problem and reframe the request when necessary. Sometimes this means taking simple data requests and turning them into more substantial projects with recommended action plans. This type of work is semi-reactive, where you still have your roadmap primarily set by stakeholders, however, it begins to take on a collegial tone where you negotiate the terms of the engagement. You’re no longer fulfilling requests unquestioningly, but rather creating a dialog with your stakeholders where you’re able to learn from one another and figure out what the priorities should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;integrated-partner&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrated Partner&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an integrated partner, the data scientist helps craft the strategic vision for the organization and has an active hand in creating the data science roadmap. To reach this stage requires deep expertise, not just in technical techniques and data, but also in the business and the politics of your company. It also means learning to spot opportunities and proactively working on projects which drive action and results in partnership with your stakeholders. This requires a high degree of empathy, being able to put yourself in the shoes of your stakeholders, and understanding the incentives that drive them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this stage you can actually set a roadmap and work towards it. You’re able to balance the needs of your stakeholders, with what’s most important based on what you agreed upon. Saying no to requests comes easily to an integrated partner, because they’ve already built trust and received buy-in from their stakeholders on what the priorities should be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Integrated partners are also more likely to challenge stakeholders on opinions they hold rather than assuming that they’re always correct. Steve Jobs was famous for cultivating a culture of debate, seeing it as a prerequisite to generating great ideas. Being the gatekeeper of the data, you have a responsibility to provide your unique point of view instead of staying silent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2170/1*OW9LZTsH-LWCjxUoR7w3UA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to recognize the fluidity of these stages. Having an integrated partner dynamic at all times with all your stakeholders can be taxing. Sometimes it’s easier to simply provide a data extract, than to try to unpack the reason behind the request. However don’t get into the habit of doing this, or you may find yourself stuck in this mode with minimal influence within the organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To build influence and transition through each stage requires you to go beyond understanding data. It requires building coalitions with stakeholders that are data savvy, and helping to convert those that are not as data inclined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means occasionally opting for a non-elegant solution which secures a quick win and establishes credibility, rather than a multi-month research project that’s unlikely to yield substantial results. Spending some time building an aggregate table and visualizing it in Tableau can buy a lot of goodwill and credibility with your stakeholders. This can then directly translate to future projects that wouldn’t have succeeded without the support from your stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2772/1*qPwYBd4Pd4FIJMc1bHK8JA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, the data scientists that are able to have the most impact, are the ones that have a deep expertise and are plugged into the wider company. They’re able to exercise influence across verticals and create coalitions to accomplish broad strategic objectives, regardless of the technical methods they employ.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/the-three-stages-of-a-data-scientist/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/the-three-stages-of-a-data-scientist/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Prioritizing Requests Using The Eisenhower Matrix</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*WVEZg8fwJX1vDCuH&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data scientists must constantly deal with the tension between short-term requests and long-term projects. Neglect the long-term projects, and you risk having minimal impact. However, neglect the short-term requests, and you may find yourself out of a job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the best data scientists are those that can split their time effectively between short-term requests and long-term projects. In practice, this can be quite difficult because there is never a shortage of questions that your stakeholders may ask. Some of these questions are urgent and important, while others are neither important nor urgent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dwight Eisenhower, a former US President, coined the idea of using urgency and importance to help him prioritize his tasks. Using the&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eisenhower.me/eisenhower-matrix/&quot;&gt; Eisenhower Matrix&lt;/a&gt;, he was able to ruthlessly prioritize his day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we’ll explore this idea, and how it can help data scientists deal specifically with stakeholder requests. We’ll go through effective strategies to deal with each of the four quadrants below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2210/1*EAJtwwDDkQVZz9IjftkN-A.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Importance / High Urgency&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically when you get these requests, everything else gets dropped. There isn’t much leeway here, except for anticipating and planning for these types of requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you know that at the end of each quarter you’re responsible for pulling data and commentary on business performance, you may find it helpful to automate some of that work. Spotting repeatable work that is automatable, especially with high importance and high urgency tasks, will help you establish credibility as someone who can accomplish objectives quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. High Importance / Low Urgency&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to high importance and low urgency requests, you may find yourself wanting to dive right in. However, the more prudent approach is to first understand what is being asked of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often you can negotiate these types of asks and whittle them down to something more manageable. For example, a marketing executive may send a laundry list of data pulls they need to understand the effects of cannibalization. The reality may be that only one or two of the data pulls are necessary to tell the story they want to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, with high importance and low urgency requests, you should strive to create a dynamic of strategic adviser, rather than that of an order taker. Having a unique point of view and leaving your stamp on the project will ensure a seat at the table for any future projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since this is a low urgency request, you should use your best judgment whether you should re-prioritize your current queue of work (including that of long-term projects). Sometimes despite the importance of the problem, you may find it better to push back and set a future date for delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Low Importance / High Urgency&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because something is urgent, does not make it important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone needs data by a certain date, you shouldn’t drop everything you’re working on to meet their deadline. Particularly if the request is of low importance (stack ranked against other requests and long-term objectives you’re working towards).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to deal with these requests is to get more information. Sometimes all it takes is a 15-minute phone call to realize that the extra work required to pull the data, may end up just being an appendix slide that never gets brought up in the meeting. In this case, you can defer to the time when the data is actually necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In cases like these, you could explore a rotation model, where each member of your team is “On-call” for these types of requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Low Importance / Low Urgency&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final, and trickiest quadrant are those requests that are of low importance and urgency. In the Eisenhower model, we would simply “Eliminate” these tasks. In a company setting, you have to be a bit more delicate with how you respond to these types of requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One easy way to defer these kinds of tasks is to put the onus on the stakeholder to do some work first. It might be a few pointed questions that require them to do some leg work before you start pulling any data. This will either buy you time, or they may lose motivation if the request wasn’t that important in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also try to delay the delivery of the work, communicating your current list of priorities and letting the stakeholder know that they should follow up with you in another week or two once things have settled down. The key is to never outright say no, but rather communicate your list of priorities to help the stakeholder understand the difficulty you may have with answering their questions at this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long-term these kinds of asks may surface the need to create self-service options. A good rule of thumb is that anytime you get asked three different times to either update analysis, or pull data to answer a similar question, you should explore a dashboarding or automated solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2210/1*mCIwWYHuIzt455Qy7HTmoA.png&quot; alt=&quot;*The Original Eisenhower Matrix*&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;The Original Eisenhower Matrix&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
So next time you have a request sitting in your email, consider which of the four quadrants it would fall under. After doing so, you can then take the corresponding measures. You’ll inevitably make some mistakes, but the alternative of trying to keep all your stakeholders happy by simply being an order taker will diminish the impact that you can have as a data scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2020/prioritizing-requests-using-the-eisenhower-matrix/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2020/prioritizing-requests-using-the-eisenhower-matrix/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Goal Setting for Data Scientists</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/3200/0*3tsM0Ft8x_e8mfJf&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting goals, particularly around the end of December can be a great way to reflect and think about what you would like to get out of your career in the new year. In this article, we’ll discuss a framework for data scientists to use to achieve their career goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since data science is an interdisciplinary field, the types of goals you set will be quite varied. A good way to partition the different types of goals is into the following three buckets: Technical, Behavioral and Professional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For technical goals, you may want to improve your understanding of certain techniques or programming languages. Behavioral goals may focus on your presentation and persuasion skills. Finally, professional goals could focus on achieving career milestones, such as a promotion or landing a new job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focus-on-what-you-can-control&quot;&gt;Focus On What You Can Control&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the type of goal you set, it’s important that you set goals that are within your locus of control. Rather than setting an external goal, such as getting a promotion, instead &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@LyskovAndrei/one-simple-tactic-from-the-stoics-for-setting-better-goals-45d8c7b392e0&quot;&gt;set internal goals&lt;/a&gt; that are within your control. For example, coming in early and pitching in to help with tasks nobody else wants to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below you can see some examples of external goals reframed into internal ones for each of the three buckets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*G-K0MgCOjgaBV-L0&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the advantages of setting internal goals is that in the event you don’t achieve your external goal (for reasons within or outside your control), you can still feel a sense of accomplishment for having completed the things that were inside your control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;be-smart-about-the-goals-you-set&quot;&gt;Be SMART about the goals you set&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*1N3XAdWQr98XL6LQ&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originating from management literature in the 1980s the SMART (Specific, Measurable, Attainable, Relevant and Time Based) framework for setting goals and objectives has seen ubiquitous use throughout business and self-development communities. This framework ensures that you’re setting goals that are within your reach, that you can track and measure over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When setting your SMART goals, you should consider the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What do I want to accomplish?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What is the pass/fail criteria?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How will I measure my progress?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Is this goal appropriate given my skill level and experience?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do I have the necessary time and resources to accomplish this?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What’re my quitting criteria?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By when would I like to accomplish this goal?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-yourself-accountable&quot;&gt;Keep Yourself Accountable&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure compliance with your goals, it can be useful to share your goals with a friend or a coach who can keep you on track. You might have a weekly check-in consisting of a phone call, or even a quick text message that summarizes your progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also a myriad of tools available for those who want to introduce a financial penalty for not hitting goals. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.beeminder.com/&quot;&gt;Beeminder&lt;/a&gt;, allows users to set goals that are either self-reported or linked to some external data source (such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rescuetime.com/&quot;&gt;RescueTime&lt;/a&gt; which tracks time spent online). So if you want to set a goal of publishing 2 data science articles a month, you could use Beeminder as a way to financially penalize yourself for not hitting that goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2296/0*Bt25GVCMuvgeSiWN&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another tool that you can use is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stickk.com/&quot;&gt;Stickk&lt;/a&gt;, which is similar to Beeminder with the added feature that whenever you fail to meet your goal, you can choose to contribute to an anti-charity (i.e. If you’re a Liverpool soccer fan, your anti-charity might be The Manchester United Fan Club ).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we enter 2020, I encourage you to think about setting at least one goal per category (technical, behavioral, and professional). When setting these goals make sure to set SMART internal goals, and have a way to keep yourself accountable, whether through social or financial penalties.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/goal-setting-for-data-scientists/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/goal-setting-for-data-scientists/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nietzche on Self-overcoming, Eternal Recurrence and Suffering</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*O8beg_3VPzPWnFoDWRu7-Q.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His work has influenced diverse groups including Marxists, Anarchists, and Conservatives. Freud, Heidegger, Jung, Hesse, Camus, Sartre, and Kafka have been influenced by his work in one form or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So who was Fredrich Nietzsche? Born in Germany in 1844, he was above all a keen observer of the human condition. Before making his mark on the world as a philosopher, he was a professor of philology at Basel University, a post he obtained at the young age of 24. It wouldn’t be until his 30s that he would strike it out on his own after having already published The Birth of Tragedy and Human, All Too Human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was during this period of independence that he would go on to write his most influential books including Thus Spoke Zarathustra, Beyond Good and Evil, On The Genealogy of Morals, and The Antichrist. His ideas were provocative and controversial. They shocked the world, particularly3 his critique of Christian morality and the Enlightenment ideas that underpinned Western philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we’ll stay away from his more controversial ideas, and instead, focus on three ideas that are relatable to readers today. They include self-overcoming, the eternal recurrence, and suffering as a catalyst for greatness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*y5FPAVB6IZei-Kbn1YWTSA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-self-overcoming&quot;&gt;1. Self-overcoming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche thought of as the great systems destroyer. He believed from birth that we are burdened with ideas and scripts which seek to confine our ability to self-actualize. In fact, the highest act of self-reflection in Nietzsche’s opinion was the revaluation of all values. This meant reconsidering your thoughts on good vs. evil, what constitutes a good life, and other foundational concepts that have been conditioned into you from a young age. To that extent, he offers the following analogy as a method for metamorphosis and coming into your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life has us start as camels, burdened with cultural baggage. These are things passed down throughout generations without question. For example, the idea that subverting authority is bad, and that being docile and meek is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To evolve beyond the camel, one must become a lion. This entails embracing nonconformity, conquering your will and creating freedom for yourself. It’s about saying “No” and shaking off excess baggage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a certain point, however, you need to evolve once again into the child, which represents innocence, forgetting and a new beginning. The child embodies the sacred yes. An entity that is capable of saying yes without reservation, even to suffering. This final stage of metamorphosis naturally leads to Nietzsche’s next idea of life-affirmation and the eternal recurrence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2560/1*vCcPbRm_y7meZy_q_NDBGQ.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-life-affirmation-and-eternal-recurrence&quot;&gt;2. Life-Affirmation and Eternal Recurrence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In “&lt;em&gt;The Gay Science”&lt;/em&gt;, one of Nietzsche’s more personal works, he offers the following thought experiment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“What, if some day or night a demon were to steal after you into your loneliest loneliness and say to you: ‘This life as you now live it and have lived it, you will have to live once more and innumerable times more; and there will be nothing new in it, but every pain and every joy and every thought and sigh and everything unutterably small or great in your life will have to return to you, all in the same succession and sequence — even this spider and this moonlight between the trees, and even this moment and I myself. The eternal hourglass of existence is turned upside down again and again, and you with it, speck of dust!’”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Nietzsche this thought experiment represented the absolute necessity of Amor Fati, learning to love and say yes to your fate. Not wanting anything to be different, not backward, not forwards, for all of eternity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He furthers his point by saying &lt;em&gt;“Did you ever say yes to a pleasure? oh my friends, then you also said yes to all the pain. All things are linked, entwined, in love with one another.”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This capacity to say yes, even to the difficulties is one that is obviously not easy. It’s much easier to deny, numb, forget, and distract yourself from that which is most painful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are whole industries built which seek to profit from one’s inability to say yes to suffering. Yet it is the exact act of saying yes to suffering, that leads one into our next idea which is the notion that suffering is a natural catalyst to greatness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*XxMfcXIvtfp8iuNVzMWkxw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-suffering-as-a-catalyst-to-greatness&quot;&gt;3. Suffering as a catalyst to greatness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you asked Nietzsche what he wished for his close ones, he would’ve responded with the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“To those human beings who are of any concern to me I wish suffering, desolation, sickness, ill-treatment, indignities — I wish that they should not remain unfamiliar with profound self-contempt, the torture of self-mistrust, the wretchedness of the vanquished: I have no pity for them, because I wish them the only thing that can prove today whether one is worth anything or not — that one endures.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now on the surface, it seems cruel to want to wish these things on those you hold dearest. Rather good health and happiness seem like the more appropriate thing to wish for. However, for Nietzsche, happiness was not an end in itself. To truly experience the beauty of life, one needed to suffer. In his mind the deeper the descent, the higher the exaltation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet this passage is also powerful in that everybody will inevitably suffer. There is no escaping this part of life. Sooner or later, you will suffer tragedies, and the best response in those situations is to turn your affliction into an advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than let these moments wreak havoc, let them act as teachers. The most spiritual human beings are often those who experience painful tragedies. These painful moments serve as a catalyst to break the shell of their previous self and allow a beautiful transformation to occur. After all, how could you become new without first becoming ashes?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The particularly nuanced point he made was that merely eliminating pain would be deemed goodness, however putting pain to work is a necessary prerequisite to greatness. Rather than dull and push away your suffering, the alternative is to transform agony and suffering into beauty and art. For generations, artists and creators of all kinds have used their pain as life fuel to create beautiful works of art and told stories that resonate with the core of what it means to be human. There is a sense that to be great, one must learn to heroically endure their suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a final note, Nietzsche knew that not all of his ideas would resonate with everyone. Instead, he writes for those individuals capable of being a value-creators and who can break out of the herd mentality. In his book Zarathustra, he uses the main character as a mouthpiece to explore several of his more intriguing ideas, and leaves the reader to ponder the following question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“I am a law only for mine own, I am not a law for all. This is now my way, where is yours?” — Zarathustra&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/Nietzsche-on-Self-overcoming,-eternal-recurrence-and-suffering/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/Nietzsche-on-Self-overcoming,-eternal-recurrence-and-suffering/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Simplifying Deep Learning with Fast.ai</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*bUZKHfAugVeXAkl0TGClCA.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep learning is a field notorious for gatekeeping. If you try to find answers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quora.com/Whats-the-most-effective-way-to-get-started-with-deep-learning&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt; on how to break into the field, you’ll likely find yourself overwhelmed with a long list of requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This often scares away potential contributors to the field, leaving us with a small fraction of the world that can consume and generate deep learning models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fast.ai&quot;&gt;Fast.ai&lt;/a&gt; is one organization that tries to address this inequity. It was founded in 2016 by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/howardjeremy/&quot;&gt;Jeremy Howard &lt;/a&gt;and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/rachel-thomas-942a7923/&quot;&gt;Rachel Thomas&lt;/a&gt;, with the goal of making deep learning more accessible. It’s primarily known for its free courses and open source library (Named &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/fastai/fastai&quot;&gt;fastai&lt;/a&gt; and built on top of Facebook’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://pytorch.org/&quot;&gt;PyTorch&lt;/a&gt; library). One of it’s most popular courses and the focus of this article is &lt;a href=&quot;https://course.fast.ai/&quot;&gt;Practical Deep Learning for Coders.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h1 id=&quot;what-i-hope-is-that-lots-of-people-will-realize-that-state-of-the-art-results-of-deep-learning-are-something-they-can-achieve-even-if-theyre-not-a-stanford-university-deep-learning-phd--jeremy-howard&quot;&gt;“What I hope is that lots of people will realize that state-of-the-art results of deep learning are something they can achieve even if they’re not a Stanford University deep learning PhD.” — &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.zdnet.com/article/fast-ais-new-software-could-radically-democratize-ai/&quot;&gt;Jeremy Howard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep learning for the uninitiated is a field that exploded in popularity due to the increased availability of data and computing resources. It’s produced state of the art results in areas such as image recognition, natural language processing, and speech recognition. It’s what powers self-driving cars, spam filters, and content recommendation systems. Deep learning at a high-level is an extension of neural networks, which use a set of inputs to train a set of weights, which then produce an output (Like classifying an image as a hot dog). In the case of deep learning, there are a lot more layers, which means a lot more weights to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*jmVjF0FnzFD8v4ZR&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast.ai introduce a top-down style approach to learning, as opposed to most other courses which start with the basics and work their way up. Intuitively this makes sense, if you’re teaching someone to play basketball, you don’t teach them the physics of the sport. Instead, you teach them enough to start playing and let their interest guide them to a deeper understanding of the sport. Similarly, within the first 45 minutes of the deep learning course, Jeremy walks you through how to build a state of the art image classifier from beginning to end. Lesson 2 has you build and productionalize your own image classifier based off of images you find on Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, you’ll get a high-level overview of their deep learning for coders course. You’ll also learn how to get the most out of the course and what this means for the future of deep learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;course-overview&quot;&gt;Course Overview&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Image Classification&lt;/strong&gt;
The first lesson covers Jeremy’s background and qualifications, the motivation for the course and possibilities after completing it. He debunks some common myths about deep learning (such as the need for lots of data and GPU) and showcases some past student projects and success stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the lesson involves building image classifiers using the fastai library to achieve state of the art accuracy. Since the class is taught in a top-down manner, the first lesson is focused on getting something working as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hiromis/notes/blob/master/Lesson1.md&quot;&gt;Lesson Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Production; SGD from scratch&lt;/strong&gt;
Continuing with the theme of image classifiers, you now get a chance to build your own image classifier. After training a model based on images you find on Google, you’re then taught how to put this model into production. The best part of this lesson is the ease of going from an idea to a production working application (&lt;a href=&quot;https://fastai-v3.onrender.com/&quot;&gt;here’s a live example of the bear image classifier built in this lesson&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the lesson consists of learning about stochastic gradient descent, by building it from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hiromis/notes/blob/master/Lesson2.md&quot;&gt;Lesson Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Multi-label; Segmentation&lt;/strong&gt;
The first part of lesson 3 gives you an overview of how to deal with multi-label classification. It also looks under the hood at some of the functions and classes used in the fastai library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you continue further into the lesson, you get into the task of image segmentation. This, of course, is used extensively in applications like self-driving cars and image tagging. You also start encountering some more theory to go with the application, such as learning why certain learning rates give better results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lesson also gives a sneak preview of natural language processing (NLP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hiromis/notes/blob/master/Lesson3.md&quot;&gt;Lesson Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. NLP; Tabular Data; Recommendation Systems&lt;/strong&gt;
Building off of the preview of NLP in lesson 3, you now learn some of the techniques that drive state of the art results. The first of which is the idea of transfer learning, which allows you to use a pre-trained model for a specific task. With this pre-trained model, you then learn how to predict negative or positive movie reviews. Based off of this simple example you’re able to achieve state of the art results, using a standardized transfer learning approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You then move on to to the topic of building deep learning models for tabular data (data you might see in a spreadsheet or relational database). The example model built is predicting whether an individual makes over $50k.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson then wraps up with an overview of recommendation systems (collaborative filtering). Jeremy explores the issue of the cold start problem (How do you recommend something to a new user?) and walks you through a simple movie recommendation example in Excel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hiromis/notes/blob/master/Lesson4.md&quot;&gt;Lesson Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Backprop; Neural Net from scratch&lt;/strong&gt;
As the title implies, this lesson is much more theory based. At this point, you start learning more about fine-tuning, unfreezing/freezing layers, regularization, using discriminative learning rates, embeddings, bias and other things that were abstracted away from you in the previous lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson wraps up with an example of a neural network built within excel, to show you exactly how it all works under the hood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hiromis/notes/blob/master/Lesson5.md&quot;&gt;Lesson Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. CNN deep dive; Ethics&lt;/strong&gt;
Lesson six continues the exploration of theory, such as the importance of dropout and why it can lead to good results. Another interesting part of this lesson is the subject of data augmentation. This is the process of taking one image and turning it into several images (as can be seen below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*8xUz8s2lBM3FM4he&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re then exposed to more theory around convolutional neural networks and receive insights into what exactly happens when a CNN is trained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last part of the lesson is dedicated to ethics in data science. This largely consists of all the ways that machine learning technologies have been misused or have the ability to be misused. Bias in facial recognition systems and translation services are two examples of misuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hiromis/notes/blob/master/Lesson6.md&quot;&gt;Lesson Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Resnet; U-net; GANs&lt;/strong&gt;
The last lesson continues to build on the theory, covering the use of Resnet and U-net to achieve state of the art results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also have a chance to be exposed to Generative Adversarial Networks, a topic that has been getting some media coverage lately through applications such as DeepFakes. GAN’s in this lesson are applied within the context of cleaning images, and you also have a chance to get an understanding of how the internals work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last section revisits NLP and explores the topic of Recurrent Neural Networks, where you get a chance to build a model that predicts the next word in a sequence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a final call to action, Jeremy recommends the following next steps as a way to solidify and build on the knowledge from the course&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*3jyr_7PbVXqdMvan&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/hiromis/notes/blob/master/Lesson7.md&quot;&gt;Lesson Notes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of the 7 lessons, you’ll have covered a wide array of topics, summarized in the image below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*sAGk4Hxgv4YCvzIm&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part 2 which is set to come out June 2019, will cover the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*XuIZv1AGiAULcNYm&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;getting-the-most-out-of-fastai&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Getting The Most Out Of Fast.ai&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get the most out of this course, it’s recommended that you watch the lectures once, and then a second or third time where you focus on replicating the notebooks. Once you feel like you’ve got a handle on things, you can start implementing these techniques with your own data and projects, or even a Kaggle competition. It’s much better to see a project through to completion, rather than leaving several half-complete ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading research papers is also a great way to take what you’ve learned and build on it. Having a PhD is not a requirement to read research papers, so don’t feel intimidated.&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arxiv-sanity.com/&quot;&gt; Arxiv Sanity Preserver&lt;/a&gt; is a great place to start, as it offers free pre-print papers from all kinds of sub-specializations in deep learning. If you’re unsure of how to read research papers, check out these two guides (&lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/getting-started-with-reading-deep-learning-research-papers-the-why-and-the-how-dfd1ac15dbc0&quot;&gt;guide one&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/ai-saturdays/how-to-read-academic-papers-without-freaking-out-3f7ef43a070f&quot;&gt; guide two&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;simplifying-deep-learning&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simplifying Deep Learning&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Fast.ai doesn’t promise that you’ll become a deep learning expert after going through their course, it does plant the initial seeds for you to start experimenting and tinkering. Many Fast.ai students go on to do a lot of interesting work, whether in AI residencies like Google, or deep learning at startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole idea behind simplifying deep learning is that it’ll allow domain experts to combine their unique expertise with deep learning. It’s not practical to think that a small group of machine learning PhD’s will be able to tackle all the problems that deep learning can solve. Especially if they don’t have the relevant domain expertise built from rigorous study and practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast.ai is a promising development in the field of deep learning. If you’re interested in deep learning it’s one of the best sources to get started and to see what is possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/simplifying-deep-learning-with-fastai/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/simplifying-deep-learning-with-fastai/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making Recommendations Stick As A Data Scientist</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/1*uSYLH1oZk8VjrV27_L6vhQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have you ever walked an audience through your recommendations, only to have them go nowhere? If you’re like most data scientists, chances are that you’ve been in this situation before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the work of a data scientist is being able to translate your work into actionable recommendations and insights for stakeholders. This means making your ideas memorable, easy to understand and impactful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we’ll explore the principles behind the book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Made-Stick-Ideas-Survive-Others-ebook/dp/B000N2HCKQ&quot;&gt;Made To Stick&lt;/a&gt;, and apply it within the context of data science. This book suggests that the best ideas follow six main principles: Simplicity, Unexpectedness, Concreteness, Credibility, Emotions, and Stories (SUCCESs). After reading this article, you’ll be able to integrate these principles into your work and increase the impact of your recommendations and insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;simple&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simple&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making an idea simple is all about stripping the idea to its core. It’s not about dumbing down, but about creating something elegant. This means that you should avoid overwhelming your audience with ideas, when you try to say 3 things, you don’t say anything at all. Another key component to making ideas simple is to avoid burying the lead. If during your analysis you find that 10% of customers contribute to 80% of revenues, lead with that key insight! You should follow an inverted pyramid approach where the first few minutes convey the most information, and as you get further you can get more nuanced. Analogies and metaphors are also a great way to get your ideas across simply and succinctly. Being able to use schemas that your audience can understand and relate to, will make it a lot more digestible. For example, a one-sentence analogy like Uber for X can capture the core message of what you’re trying to convey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unexpected&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unexpected&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unexpected idea is one that violates people’s expectations and takes advantage of surprise. You can do this in several ways, one of which is making people commit to an answer, then falsifying it. For example, asking to guess how much time employees spend doing a task you’re looking to automate before revealing the real answer. Another way to generate interest and leverage the unexpected principle is to use mysteries since they lead to “aha” moments. This might take the form of starting your presentation with a short story, that you don’t resolve until the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;concrete&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concrete&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstractness is the enemy of understanding for non-experts. It’s your job as the data scientist to make your recommendations and insights more concrete. A key to understanding is using concrete images and explaining ideas in terms of human actions and senses. The natural enemy of concreteness is the curse of knowledge. As data scientists, we need to fight the urge to overwhelm our audiences with unnecessary technical information. For example, reporting on the Root Mean Squared Error of a model, may not be as helpful as breaking up the language into more concrete terms that anyone can understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;credible&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credible&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adding credibility to your recommendations can take three forms. The first is the most common one when we think of credibility, which is leveraging experts to back up claims or assertions. Another way is using anti-authorities who are real people with powerful stories. For example, if you’re talking about the dangers of smoking, the story of someone who suffers from lung cancer will be a lot more impactful than a sterile statistic. The third ways of adding credibility to your story is by outsourcing the credibility of your point to your audience. This means creating a testable claim that the audience can try out. For example making the claim that customers from region A, take up 80% more customer support time than any other region. In posing this claim, your audience can confirm this claim which can make it easier to lead to your recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;emotions&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emotions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weaving an emotional component to your ideas is all about getting people to care. Humans are naturally wired to feel for humans, not for abstractions. As a result, one individual often trumps a composite statistic. Another component of emotions is tapping into the group identities that your audience conforms to. By keeping those identities in mind, you can tie in the relevant associations and evoke certain schemas that your audience will be most receptive to. For example, if you know one of your audience members is a stickler for numbers and wants to see a detailed breakdown of how you arrived at certain conclusions, then adding an appendix may be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;stories&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stories&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humans have been telling stories for centuries and they have proven to be one of the most effective teaching methods. If you reflect on the books you’ve read in the past 5 years, you’re more likely to remember the interesting stories rather than objective facts. When weaving stories into your recommendations, make sure to build tension and don’t give everything away all at once. Another useful tactic is telling stories which act as springboards to other ideas. Creating open-ended stories that your audience can build on is a great way for them to get a sense of ownership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time you’re tasked with distilling your insights or pitching recommendations, keep in mind these six principles and you’ll be creating simple, unexpected, concrete, credentialed emotional stories in no time!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/making-recommendations-stick-as-a-data-scientist/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/making-recommendations-stick-as-a-data-scientist/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Satirical Take On a Post-Scarcity Society</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2000/0*aRvLTi7KfxsfQptr.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;[Player Piano](https://www.amazon.ca/Player-Piano-Novel-Kurt-Vonnegut/dp/0385333781)&quot; /&gt;*
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.ca/Player-Piano-Novel-Kurt-Vonnegut/dp/0385333781&quot;&gt;Player Piano&lt;/a&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to be human in a world where automation has devalued almost all human labor? This is the central theme of Kurt Vonnegut’s 1952 novel, Player Piano. In the beginning, we’re introduced to Paul Proteus, an engineering manager of a plant in futuristic New York who is a rising star within his company. This is partly because of his famous father who kickstarted the mechanization of the entire country. In this world, machines have gotten to the point where they do everything from mundane chores like house cleaning, to deciding your career path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the world is divided into engineers who maintain and create machines, and the rest of the population who work in reclamation works or in the army. The latter two which serve no real purpose, other than giving people something to do. As the book progresses, we watch as Paul grows disillusioned with the state of things, and begins to contemplate a life without machines. He’s soon persuaded by one of his former colleagues to join a rebellion and become its figurehead. When the rebellion is in full swing, it soon gets out of control and we see the widespread destruction of even machines whose sole purpose was only to make orange juice. Yet, surprisingly, towards the end of the book, the same people who destroyed the machines are now trying to fix and repair them. At this point, Paul and his conspirators realize their rebellion is over and turn themselves over to the army.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Paul’s story was the main plot line, there were also several sub-plot lines which provide for some interesting commentary. One was the American tour of the Shah of Bratpuhr, a spiritual leader of an un-mechanized nation. The goal of this tour was to convince the Shah of the value that mass mechanization can provide for him and his people. Throughout his tour, there are several funny mistranslations. He often calls workers on the side of the road “&lt;em&gt;Takaru&lt;/em&gt;”, or slaves in his language. His translator tries and fails to correct him, stating that they are in fact citizens employed by the government. Although it’s quite clear that the mechanization has turned a large swath of society into indentured slaves. Another interesting scene is when the Shah asks a spiritual riddle to the giant computer brain EPICAC. In his religion, the entity that can answer the riddle will signify the arrival of an &lt;em&gt;“all-wise-god&lt;/em&gt;”. In this case, the machine fails to provide an answer, and the Shah is dismayed to realize that it is, in fact, a false god. Despite all the technological advances, the computer is still unable to answer our deepest questions or give life meaning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you think about what the world will look like post-mechanization, there may be some obvious advantages. Dangerous work will be non-existent, and people may have more free time to explore their interests. Yet the implicit assumption here is that in this post-scarcity society, people will be able to create meaning for themselves. It’s clear however that the citizens of this world are not up to the task, as alcoholism and suicide are rampant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book draws an interesting parallel as well to the story of the Native Americans and settlers. After their lands were taken over, these once proud people felt displaced. No longer were great hunters given an opportunity to hunt and prove their worth. Leaders could no longer lead due to an imbalance that guns gave to the settlers. In this new world, their old values didn’t apply anymore. Similarly, in this futuristic world, the values of a pre-mechanized America were not compatible with the realities of an under-utilized workforce. Friedrich Nietzsche, a philosopher from the 19th century talks about the need for a revaluation of values. While this call for a revaluation of values was in the context of reevaluating Christian values, a similar case can be made in this post-scarcity society. The only way to prevent a stark class divide and massive inequity is to reevaluate all our closest held values and beliefs. Beyond this task, which in itself is a herculean effort, it would be almost impossible to stem the tide of automation and its consequences. Any attempt to regulate it will only lead to other countries adopting mechanization and leaving the laggard countries in the dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s quite clear that despite this book having been written almost 70 years ago, it has great relevance for our current society which is increasingly mechanizing its workforce. While it’s true that technology has often added more jobs than it’s replaced in the past, that may not always be the case going forward. As such it’s important to start thinking about what it means to live in a post-scarcity society. Specifically, looking at the values that we and society hold, and whether the institutions we have set up are conducive to those values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a high likelihood that the future will lead to widening inequality if we don’t navigate mass mechanization carefully. Individuals who find themselves displaced due to no fault of their own may struggle to find work and meaning. Those unable to find meaning will likely try to distract themselves whether through drugs, alcohol or some other means. Those who reap the windfall of this technological boom will be insulated from any of the fallout. While this may seem like a bleak vision of the future, it does not seem at all inconceivable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The alternative path is a much harder one and which in itself will bring a lot of pain and turmoil but may at the very least lead to a brighter future. Specifically, the destruction and creation of new institutions and values. In a world where machines have mechanized most labor, does it make sense to have the educational institutions we have? How about the value systems and incentive structures, that may have served us well in the past but may not be suited for the future ahead? These are all important questions to ask, and while we may not always like the answer, Vonnegut does a brilliant job of painting a vision of a future where our values stay the same, but the environment changes drastically. Ultimately Player Piano leaves us with the sense that if we fail to address these fundamental issues than the future may indeed be quite bleak for the majority of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/a-satirical-take-on-a-post-scarcity-society/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/a-satirical-take-on-a-post-scarcity-society/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why Data Scientists Need To Lead Data Evangelism Efforts</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/3094/1*Y8uBrDxsQ-qz-Yb20vJx5A.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When is the last time you helped someone with a request that they could’ve easily done themselves? If you’re like most data scientists, you’re likely having to deal with ad hoc requests on a fairly frequent basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to minimize the number of these requests is to educate and empower your colleagues through data evangelism efforts. Every organization is different and depending on which stage of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cio.com/article/3077871/the-four-stages-of-the-data-maturity-model.html&quot;&gt;Data Maturity Model&lt;/a&gt; your company is in, one data evangelism initiative may have a higher return on investment than others. For example, if you’re getting variations of a simple SQL request (E.g. what are sales in region x during these days?), then creating a SQL workshop may prove to be a great use of your time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides making your colleagues self sufficient, data evangelism can also lead to strengthening your technical team and promote awareness of your work. Inviting people to share their work in the context of a learning lunch or a newsletter, is a great way to raise awareness and allows for people to showcase their knowledge. External stakeholders may also benefit from greater insight into what exactly the data science team does, and how they can help them achieve their business objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a data scientist, you should be leading the way when it comes to evangelizing your data and encouraging data-driven decision making. With the importance of data evangelism in mind, below are six ideas for initiatives that you can start at your company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-workshops&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Workshops&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself regularly dealing with simple requests that can be done with some basic training, then it may be time to consider hosting a workshop. Educating line of business stakeholders on the basics of SQL and the mechanics of your data collection and storage may lead to huge time savings on your part. Other topics could include an overview of basic business intelligence tools such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.periscopedata.com/&quot;&gt;Periscope&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tableau.com/&quot;&gt;Tableau&lt;/a&gt;, or even a workshop describing the basics of how your predictive models make decisions. The key here is to engage, educate and inspire your colleagues to continue learning on their own. Having office hours during specific times of the week may be another useful way to keep engagement high and create time to answer questions. This way you can also batch questions, and avoid context switching during the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-newsletter&quot;&gt;2. &lt;strong&gt;Newsletter&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a newsletter, you can either focus on internal topics (highlighting projects and internal team updates), external (industry trends), or a hybrid of the two. Having a way to communicate what your team is working on is a great way to raise awareness and coordinate action with others in your company. Similarly, highlighting developments in your field may lead to someone outside of your immediate team to come up with a novel idea worth exploring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-research-paper-club&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Research Paper Club&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you start working it can be difficult to continue learning and staying on top of the latest developments. In this way, research paper clubs can serve as a useful accountability tool. It may also lead to some interesting ideas that impact your technical roadmap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-learning-lunches&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Learning Lunches&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inviting internal or external speakers is a great way to get a fresh perspective and offer a platform for others to share what they’re working on. The goal could be anything from highlighting unique insights from people outside of your team, to generating interesting discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-data-hackathons&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Data Hackathons&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opening your data to others in your company can be useful if you want to brainstorm new ways to visualize data or different approaches to building predictive models. Sometimes it takes someone who doesn’t look at the same data every day to come up with a novel insight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;6-documentation&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Documentation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important step in educating your colleagues is creating documentation on topics that come up frequently. This will also be an invaluable tool when on-boarding new teammates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A culture which educates and empowers employees through data evangelism efforts will be one that will reap both explicit and implicit benefits for many years to come. Sometimes it’s as simple as walking through a business stakeholder through the mechanics of a model you have in production to get them to understand how it’s happening, as opposed to having them to think it’s black-box magic. With increased transparency, that business stakeholder may be more likely to cooperate and may even come up with some new applications that you hadn’t thought of before. These types of efforts among the ones listed above will ultimately lead to increased credibility and trust. Without these two things, no matter how great your technical abilities are, your ability to impact the company will be stunted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have other ideas for data evangelism efforts, please share in the comments below!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/why-data-scientists-need-to-lead-data-evangelism-efforts/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/why-data-scientists-need-to-lead-data-evangelism-efforts/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Guide to Full Immersion Learning</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Learn how to accelerate your learning and gain fluency in any subject!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you learn? If you’re anything like the average person, you may enroll in a course, or buy a book and take some notes. But is the reliance on one or two sources the best way to learn?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alternative is that of full immersion learning. This approach is all about adding as many diverse learning resources as possible and taking an active role in your learning. Full immersion learning consists of three parts: Learning the Vocabulary, Building A Tribe and Applying Your Knowledge. After reading and putting this approach in practice, you’ll be ready to tackle any subject of your interest!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/2294/1*raakTIkMIp7TzIblU7ovlQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning-the-vocabulary&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Learning The Vocabulary&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first goal when starting to learn something new is to familiarize yourself with the vocabulary. Additionally understanding the concepts, foundational ideas, key figures, and the history, will give you a deeper appreciation for what you’re learning. It’ll also allow you to form new insights and ask questions that go beyond the surface level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best ways to acquire this vocabulary is to approach multiple resources simultaneously. For example, you may be enrolled in a technical machine learning course, while also watching West World, and listening to a podcast which interviews experts in machine learning. By adding multiple resources you’ll start to notice common ideas and phrases, presented in different formats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some resources that can help when you’re starting out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Books&lt;/strong&gt; — Don’t restrict yourself to only non-fiction! Some of the most thought-provoking and educational books can come out of fiction. Neal Stephenson is a renowned author of fiction, who packs his books with tons of educational content. Take some time to also read biographies of key figures and the history of the field you’re learning. This will give you some context of how it started and where it may be going.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Courses&lt;/strong&gt; - Online or in-person courses are a great way to familiarize yourself with vocabulary in a more structured setting. They also offer an opportunity for you to get to know other students who are on the same learning journey. There are any number of Massively Open Online Classrooms, some of which are free and others paid.&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/&quot;&gt; Coursera&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edx.org/&quot;&gt; Edx&lt;/a&gt;, and&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udemy.com/&quot;&gt; Udemy&lt;/a&gt; all offer a diverse set of courses that will likely cover the subject you’re interested in learning.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Media&lt;/strong&gt; — On top of courses you may also find short or long-form content in the form of podcasts, videos, and articles that will help complement your learning. As with books, try to expand your scope beyond the technical. If you’re learning biology, then it may be interesting to watch sci-fi tv movies which grapple with ethical dilemmas associated with our increasing mastery over biology. Documentaries are also great for getting a short overview of a field and familiarizing yourself with top experts. Also, make sure to search YouTube since there’s a high likelihood that someone has created a channel to help you learn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practice and Testing&lt;/strong&gt; - One of the best ways to increase your vocabulary and understanding is through practice and testing. This can be as simple as creating flashcards for terms or can involve more practical problems related to your field.&lt;a href=&quot;https://getatomi.com/staffroom/what-is-active-recall-and-how-effective-is-it/&quot;&gt; Active recall&lt;/a&gt; has proven to be one of the best techniques to solidify your learning, so make sure to take advantage of this!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;building-a-tribe&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Building A Tribe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you feel like you have a good grasp of vocabulary, it’s time to meet some people! The three groups of individuals that you should seek out are Mentors, Peers, and Mentees. Building a learning tribe that consists of these three groups will help you confront holes in your knowledge, while also receiving guidance and support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentors are people who have achieved some level of mastery or expertise in the field you’re interested in. They can help you identify areas of weakness, answer specific questions and provide milestones for you to strive towards. Peers are other learners who have a similar level of expertise. The advantage of having a peer is that you’ll often encounter similar learning challenges, allowing each of you an opportunity to teach and learn from one another. Mentees are people who may be just starting out. Richard Feynman, a Nobel winning physicist, was known for saying “*If you can’t explain something in simple terms, you don’t understand it.”. *Thus mentees provide an opportunity for you to test how thoroughly you actually understand something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some areas you can find these people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Online Communities&lt;/strong&gt; — &lt;a href=&quot;https://slofile.com/&quot;&gt;Slack&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://discordservers.com/&quot;&gt;Discord&lt;/a&gt; are frequently used by niche communities who want to have to create a more intimate community. While there are plenty of Facebook online communities, they aren’t nearly as versatile or engaging as the former two. Other options include Twitter, which often has its own sub-Twitter communities, Quora where you can ask and answer questions, and Medium where you can identify experts who write about the content you’re interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Offline Communities&lt;/strong&gt; — Depending on what you’re learning and where you live, there’s a good chance that there exists some sort of offline community filled with similarly motivated learners. Take a look at websites such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meetup.com/&quot;&gt;Meetup&lt;/a&gt;, Facebook’s discover event feature or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.ca/&quot;&gt;Eventbrite&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Paid Mentor&lt;/strong&gt; — A more effective way of finding a mentor is to pay for one. Informal mentors may not have the ability to meet with you regularly or have a background in mentoring. Paid mentors, on the other hand, will have had lots of experience working with people of your skill level and can meet with you on your own terms. Depending on the subject, you can either find specific websites for mentors (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://hackhands.com/&quot;&gt;HackHands&lt;/a&gt; a website for programming mentors) or more general websites such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.superprof.com/&quot;&gt;Super Prof&lt;/a&gt; which have a wide variety of teachers and mentors.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;applying-your-knowledge&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Applying Your Knowledge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve learned the vocabulary, and formed your learning tribe, it’s time to apply your knowledge! This is an important step in your learning journey as it allows you to consolidate your learning, and get feedback from others. Whether you choose to apply your knowledge through writing, programming, or another way of expressing your knowledge, the key is to weave in your learning in a way that feels authentic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are any number of ways for you to apply your knowledge, however, three general areas are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Experiences&lt;/strong&gt; — Applying your knowledge within the context of experiences could involve giving a talk to share your knowledge with a wider audience, or organizing a dinner group with the intention of discussing your subject in depth. Showcasing your knowledge by creating experiences also serves as a great way to identify mentors, peers, and mentees.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Products&lt;/strong&gt; - Creating a product whether free or paid, is a fantastic way of consolidating your knowledge. Products could range from mobile apps, websites, physical products, or even an online course. An example using an abstract subject such as Ethics might be a mobile app that helps users crowdsource advice related to ethical problems in their life. Inside the app, you could write articles explaining various ethical frameworks that would serve to educate users and help them make morally informed decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Media&lt;/strong&gt; — Distribution channels for content such as Medium, LinkedIn, Quora and Youtube all serve as a great way to share your learning with a wider audience. You might start by creating content and guides to help out learners who are just starting out or simply answering questions that other people have. This will allow you to clarify your thinking, and get feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After following this framework, all that’s left is to climb the ladder of competency in your given field. At a certain point in your learning journey, you may even benefit from learning another complementary field that can help you deepen and generate new insights. For example, if you’ve spent the last 6 months learning to program, you may benefit from learning about Product so that you can improve the products that you build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in more tactical advice on learning, I’d recommend reading my other article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/age-of-awareness/learning-how-to-learn-a727f7b96f53&quot;&gt;learning how to learn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2019/A-Guide-To-Full-Immersion-Learning/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2019/A-Guide-To-Full-Immersion-Learning/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
